<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-martinsen-ice-tls-candidates-latest"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ICE TLS">TLS Candidates for ICE</title>
    <author fullname="Paal-Erik Martinsen" initials="P.E" surname="Martinsen">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Philip Pedersens Vei 22</street>
          <city>Lysaker</city>
          <region>Akershus</region>
          <code>1325</code>
          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>
        <email>palmarti@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Nathan Buckles" initials="N." surname="Buckles">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2250 East President George Bush Highway</street>
          <city>Richardson</city>
          <region>Texas</region>
          <code>75082-3550</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>nbuckles@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
        
    <date/>

    <workgroup>ICE</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document introduces TLS candidates to ICE.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        In use-cases where media is terminated by a public reachable
        server it is desirable to be able to negotiate a TLS
        connection in addition to UDP as described in ICEbis <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ice-rfc5245bis"/> and TCP as described in
        ICE-TCP <xref target="RFC6544"/>. This will increase the
        chances of successfully traversing any firewall between the
        client and the public server.
      </t>
      <t>
        Due to the problems associated with p2p connections and TCP
        (Synchronously opening up the two necessary pinholes at two
        different NAT/FWs), this specification focuses on the use case
        where one side is publicly reachable and runs ICE-lite.
      </t>
      
    </section>
  
    <section anchor="notation" title="Notational Conventions">
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
        in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification uses terminology defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ice-rfc5245bis">ICEbis</xref>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview_of_operations" title="Overview of Operations">
      <t>
        ICE performs connectivity checks between clients and
        servers. ICE candidates are usually exchanged via SDP and
        connectivity checks are performed on each candidate pair.  In
        the scenario where the client implements a full ICE stack and
        the server implements a ICE lite stack.  The client is in the
        ICE controlling role, so the client has ultimate control over
        which candidate pair is selected.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ice-tls-candidates" title="ICE-TLS-Candidates">      
      <t>
        The grammar for ICE candidates in SDP is described in ICEbis
        and ICE-TCP.  For TLS candidates, we update the
        grammar as follows:
        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
          transport = “UDP” / “TCP” / “TLS” / transport-extension
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure> 
        Candidate priority is calculated using the standard formula
        with UDP having higher priority than TCP or TLS, and TCP
        having higher priority than TLS. 
      </t>
      <t>
        Example ICE candidates from a client:
        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
          
   a=candidate:1 1 UDP 2113933823 10.19.1.236 20124 typ HOST
   a=candidate:2 1 TCP 2113933567 10.19.1.236 20000 typ HOST
   a=candidate:3 1 TLS 2113933322 10.19.1.236 20000 typ HOST \
   fingerprint sha-1;XX:YY:ZZ
   52:A7:60:90:B2:3E:79:43:08:77:F0:80:C6:14:E2:1B:87:16:B3:B1
   ]]></artwork>
        </figure> 
        
        Example ICE candidates from a server:
        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
          
  a=candidate:0 1 UDP 2130706431 23.253.251.168 33434 typ host
  a=candidate:8 1 TCP 1962934271 23.253.251.168 33434 typ host tcptype
  passive a=candidate:16 1 TLS 1459376510 23.253.251.168 443 typ host
  \ tcptype passive fingerprint sha-1;XX:YY:ZZ ]]></artwork>
        </figure> 
        Note that the server TCP and TLS candidates are always marked
        as passive indicating that the client always initiates the TCP
        connection.  For TLS candidates both the client and server
        MUST include the fingerprint attribute that has the following
        syntax largely borrowed from Comedia over TLS in SDP <xref
        target="RFC4572"/>.
        
        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
          extension-att-name = “fingerprint”
          extension-att-value = hash-func “;” fingerprint
          hash-func =  "sha-1" / "sha-224" / "sha-256" / token                              
          fingerprint =  2UHEX *(":" 2UHEX)                              
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure> 
        The certificates exchanged as part of the TLS handshake should
        be validated against the given fingerprint as a means of
        identifying the remote TLS participant.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="sending-packets" title="Sending Packets">
      <t>
        Various types of packets (RTP, RTCP, SRTP, SRTCP, STUN, DTLS,
        BFCP) are sent over the different transport types in different
        ways.
      </t>  
      <t>
        When using UDP transport all packets except BFCP are sent
        directly over UDP as individual UDP datagrams.  BFCP packets
        are sent directly over UDP when the BFCP m-line is not DTLS
        enabled.  BFCP packets are sent as DTLS payload when the
        m-line is DTLS enabled.
      </t>
      <t>
        When using TCP transport all packets except BFCP are sent
        directly over the TCP connection using RTP and RTCP over
        Connection-Oriented Transport <xref target="RFC4571"/>
        framing.  BFCP packets are sent using this framing when the
        BFCP m-line is not DTLS enabled.  BFCP packets are sent as
        DTLS payload when the m-line is DTLS enabled.
      </t>
      <t>
        When using TLS transport all packets except BFCP are sent as
        TLS payload using rfc4571 framing.  BFCP packets are sent
        using rfc4571 framing when the BFCP m-line is not DTLS
        enabled.  BFCP packets are sent as DTLS payload when the
        m-line is DTLS enabled.
      </t>
      <t>
        In the case of SRTP/SRTCP and TLS, each packet will be double
        encrypted.  On the encryption side the SRTP/SRTCP encryption
        and authentication is done first and the TLS encryption is
        done second.  On the decryption side, the TLS decryption is
        done first and the SRTP/SRTCP decryption is done second.
      </t>
      <t>
        When a media or application m-line is negotiated (in SDP) as
        using DTLS, a DTLS handshake will be performed regardless of
        the chosen transport type.  In the case of a TLS transport,
        the DTLS packets will be sent as TLS payload.  This creates a
        slightly strange end result of DTLS over TLS but this allows
        the system as a whole to operate in the same manner regardless
        of the chosen transport type.
      </t>
    </section>      

    <section anchor="http-proxy" title="HTTP Proxy">      
      <t>
        Some firewalls will block arbitrary UDP, TCP, or TLS traffic,
        but will allow TLS traffic via an HTTP proxy.  When an HTTP
        proxy is configured on the client (or host operating system)
        and TLS ICE candidates have been exchanged between the client
        and server, then the client should initiate an HTTP CONNECT to
        the proxy server before sending TLS traffic.
      </t>
      <t>
        The client provides the IP and TLS port of the server to the
        HTTP proxy (in the form of a generated HTTP URL).  It is quite
        likely that the TLS port of the server must be 443 (standard
        HTTPS port) for this operation to work.  After the proxy
        server returns 200 the client may send the TLS along the
        established TCP connection with the proxy server and the TLS
        will be forwarded (intact) to the server.  (There is a wiki
        page at https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_tunnel, but no
        real standards to point to). 
      </t>
      <t>
        The use of an HTTP proxy is largely invisible to the server.
        The server will see the IP address port used by the HTTP proxy
        instead of the client, but this will be handled normally as
        part of ICE processing.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rtcp-mux" title="RTCP Multiplexing">      
      <t>
        It is desirable (and in some cases required) that RTCP and RTP
        be transmitted over the same port.  This behavior is
        negotiated in SDP as described in Multiplexing RTP and RTCP
        <xref target="RFC5761"/>.  It is highly recommended that all
        clients support rtcp-mux.  Clients that do not support
        rtcp-mux may not be able to use TLS and HTTP proxies for
        connectivity.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="compability" title="Compatibility">
      <t>
        TODO: How will this affect old clients?
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        SDP?
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        The security considerations described in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ice-rfc5245bis"/> are still valid. 

        TODO: ANY TLS attacs we should care about?  TODO: SRTP? Do we
        need it even if we use TLS, yes probably. (Changing paths and
        so on?)
      </t>
      
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
      </t>
    </section>
    
  </middle>
  
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-ice-rfc5245bis"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4571"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4572"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5761"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6544"?>   
 </references>

    
  </back>
</rfc>
